[MUSIC PLAYING]
COLTON OGDEN: All right.
Welcome to GD50.
This is lecture 10.
Today we'll be talking about "Portal."
So "Portal" is a very iconic
game, I think most of us
have probably seen it before.
The gist is you have a portal gun, a gun
that shoots these elliptical portals.
If you look through
one, you can effectively
see what is coming out the other one,
which is pretty cool, and vise versa.
And then, if you walk
in between the portals,
you'll actually be
teleported to the other side.
And so, they achieve a lot
of really interesting effects
with some pretty cool tricks and stuff.
And actually Valve
themselves will be coming
to give a talk on a
lot of the technology
that they used on the second.
So we can get a glimpse into
their version of "Portal."
My version of "Portal" is
a bit simpler, but we'll
look at a lot of the
same sort of principles
and see how I accomplished
a lot of the same things.
So this is also the last
lecture of the semester,
and we've covered a lot of ground.
I have a few screenshots here
to show some of the games
that we've talked about.
The very first game was "Pong,"
and we've come sort of a long way.
We have gone through very simple
arcadey Atari-like games like this,
and have gone and created
worlds effectively.
And now we're in 3D, we're doing
all kinds of awesome stuff.
But this was where we
started the course.
And it's kind of fun to look
back and see where we've come.
So here, we talked about scoring
and just effectively drawing shapes
onto the screen, then we transition
to "Flappy Bird" or "50 Bird,"
and we had sprites and characters.
And we talked about scrolling and
infinite level procedural generation
type algorithms, and that was fun.
We took things a step higher
than that with "Breakout"
where we had the same
sort of procedural ideas
in the context of a
very famous arcade game.
We talked about particle
systems and some arcade style
physics and high scores.
Then we went into puzzle games.
We talked about Match Three"
and how to actually calculate
what goes on to determine
whether we have gotten a match
and how to clear blocks
and how to tween things,
do operations over time,
sort of this A synchronicity.
Then we went into probably what
is my favorite lecture, which
was "Super Mario
Brothers," and we talked
about how to create procedural
worlds that all look very different
with some very simple algorithms.
And then we had triggers and
events sort of happening.
Then "Legend of Zelda" came, and we
had this infinite dungeon algorithm.
And we had enemies
walking around that we
could use a sword on, so it felt more
like an actual action game, action RPG.
Then took a brief look at physics in the
context of Box 2D with "Angry Birds,"
and I still remember the
ball pit example was probably
my favorite part of that.
And then probably the most
complicated example of the semester
was "Pokemon," where we actually
had a semi full turn based
parallel system, and random encounters,
and like a little world where there's
actually two main stages to our
world where there was the field
and the battle scene, which is a
very common thing to have in RPGs.
Following "Pokemon," which was
the most complicated codebase,
we went into Unity, which
was our first foray into 3D.
And even though we were
just exploring 2.5D,
we still got a chance to look at how
does the Unity engine work and how do
we get actual 3D models onto the screen?
And we put together a very simple
"Flappy Bird" esque game so
that we could sort of
recycle prior ideas.
Last week, we looked at "Dread 50,"
which was sort of a Dreadhall's horror
inspired game where we
got to look at lighting
and how to actually transition between
scenes and use some basic UI in Unity.
And today, we'll be talking about
how to create a game similar to this,
although much simpler.
Today is mostly just a tech
demo more than anything else.
But this is a screenshot of
the actual game "Portal."
And as you can see, they do a
lot of really cool fancy things.
They have a portal on
sort of a slope, they
have another portal coming out of
the front wall over back there.
There are different colors so you can
differentiate between left and right,
orange and blue.
They have sort of this
object here on the side,
and I believe that's to shoot
cubes out, which this here
is a cube which you can
then grab with your gun
and then shoot it through portals and
see it come in and out of portals,
which is pretty cool.
And we'll talk today about how to create
a simple version of this, primarily
just the aspect of how do I create a
portal that looks out of another scene
and see it updating in real time?
And how do I teleport and get
back and forth between the portals
and carry a weapon and then shoot a ray
that will actually place a portal where
I want to in the game world?
So today, some of the
topics we'll talk about.
So one, holding a weapon.
So we've used a first
person controller, and this
is a very easy and simple thing to do.
But it helps illustrate
what parenting is.
And so we'll talk about that.
Ray casting is the actual shooting
out of a ray from your object
to Z direction forward.
So you have an X and a Y, which are
sort of the angle at which you're
moving around.
But then you have Z, which if
you're using the forward vector
from your character, it's going
to be forward in the z-axis
wherever you're looking effectively.
And so that allows us to cast a ray,
in that sense, which just means shoot
a straight line, an invisible
straight line from that point,
and wherever that point
intersects with an object,
we can get some information
about that and then do
whatever work we need to do.
In this case, take a portal prefab and
just affix it to the wall, basically.
Rotate it from its default
position, and then just
put it flat up against the wall.
Texture masking is how we're going
to achieve this portal effect, right?
Because when we create what's called a
render texture in Unity, which here's
the third bullet, a render
texture just means a texture
that we're rendering to with a camera.
So rather than have a texture be an
asset in your game, in your hierarchy
with something that
you made in Photoshop,
you can actually dynamically
create it at runtime
with what the camera is seeing.
And Unity gives this to
you for free very easily
with what's called a render texture,
which is just another asset type.
And then texture masking is
effectively the same thing
as stenciling where we can choose
certain pixels of an object to delete.
In this case, we create a texture that's
white in the center and then black
around the edges in an elliptical shape.
And what that allows us to do
is tell it with a simple shader,
don't render these pixels when you
actually render the render texture,
just render the ones in the middle.
And so, that's how we achieve
an ellipse, just by effectively
discarding the pixels in the outer rim.
Decals is an idea in 3D games
where a decal is just something
that you affix a texture or some
object that you affixed to a surface.
In this case, we'll be using
decals to act as our portal.
So our portals are actually
just going to be decals.
They're just meshes with a
render texture affixed to them.
And then all we need to do is just slap
them onto a wall whenever we shoot it,
and we get a ray that
intersects with the wall.
And that will have the
effect of actually making
it look like we're putting a portal
on a wall, when in reality, we're
just taking a mesh and we're kind of
just like slapping it onto a wall.
Some other examples of decals that
you've probably seen in other games
are, for example, bullet holes,
which use the same principle.
Teleporting is very easy,
although the FPS controller sort
of complicates things a little bit.
So we'll talk about how and about sort
of solving the problem of teleporting
in a way that makes sense.
It's usually just as simple as setting
something's transforms position
to another transforms
position, setting the rotation
to the transforms rotation.
But the FPS controller
cashes its rotation data,
so in order to that
teleport cleanly you sort of
have to override some default behavior.
And lastly, we'll take
a look at some new tools
that Unity has introduced with
2018 0.1 Pro Builder and Pro
Grids, which allow you to actually
model geometry in the scene.
And this is what the assignment
is going to be focused on.
Because going forward, I foresee it
being a major part of modern unity
development and or prototyping.
The ability to model your scene in Unity
without needing a third party program
heavily optimizes the
actual creation process
and allows you to do
easy, what's called,
"gray boxing," meaning create a level in
your game engine and then prototype it,
test it, make sure that it's actually
game playable right off the bat.
That's called "gray boxing."
But first, let's get a demo.
So does anybody want to come up here
and play my implementation of "Portal?"
So James is landlocked.
All right James, you're not landlocked.
Let's go.
All right, so I'm going to
go ahead and set that up.
And so disclaimer, there's
actually a bug in this
as well, so I'm curious to see
if you can spot what the bug is.
Go ahead and hit play
as soon as you're ready.
And then the mouse on the right
will be your angle your portal.
So we see here I have a character
with a portal gun created.
So James, if you shoot a wall with the
left mouse, that will create a portal.
And then if use the right mouse--
so that's one other bug.
So let's go ahead and restart
the program, actually.
So that's one bug.
And so, if we avoid stepping
into a portal that's there--
and this this could be
fixed in a couple of ways.
So now you have two
portals basically created.
Do you see what's wrong with the portal
as it is here, both of these portals
actually?
Oh actually, no, I'm sorry, these
portals are actually completely right.
But walk through them.
And I will show you--
OK, so you can see it
works pretty well, right?
You can not only see your character
rendering completely or moving
in real time when the other texture,
but you can jump through them
or walk through them.
You can jump with spacebar
if you want, and that'll
teleport you throughout
the other end so you
see from the perspective
of the other portal.
But if we try shooting
one of the other walls
for instance, like one
of these white walls,
you can see something weird
happens with this particular wall.
Anything strike you as
odd about that portal?
Anybody?
It's upside down.
And so if you walk through it
though, it works perfectly fine.
Now the reason that it's upside down,
I spent probably like 10, 15 hours
trying to figure out why
this is, it's in a state
of what's called "gimbal lock."
So this prefab right here, there's
three axis of rotation in 3D space.
And if you perform a
rotation in some odd way,
there are these things
called oiler angles,
which are your angles of rotation
about the x,y and z-axis.
And you can sort of
think of them as sort
of being able to rotate
interdependently.
But there is a situation
in which you can--
for some reason, Unity's internal
representation of a rotation
can get messed up by
manipulating these angles.
And so, you can actually
lock two axes together such
that rotating-- like for example,
in this case, it's Z and Y,
they both rotate each other.
And so you're unable to get, in this
particular case, the portal to rotate
about the axis that lets it look
like its right side up based
on the wall's surface normal.
And so, had I maybe another week,
I probably could have debugged it,
but I had to leave it in.
Unfortunately, I ran out of time.
But the interesting thing is if
you do shoot that same wall--
so try and shoot that
wall, the other wall with--
like put both portal on the
buggy wall, so the right wall.
It's only that wall, by
the way, for some reason.
So notice that now its right side up.
So if you shoot both portals on
the same wall, that buggie wall,
they do get right side up.
And I for the life of me couldn't
ascertain exactly as to why.
I know it's gimbal lock.
Unfortunately, I was unable
to debug it quite in time.
But every other wall, including
the ceiling and the floor,
will work if you shoot
a portal up on them.
So you can create one up there,
and then you can jump through it.
See how it's looking down, and
then it'll put you at the top.
And altogether, minus the weird single
wall that gimbal locks the portal,
we have a pretty
functional implementation
of a very basic portal game, right?
We have this model here is
parenting to the camera.
So it's always going to look in the
exact same direction as the camera.
We shoot a ray from the
tip of the gun, and then
whenever that ray intersects with a
plane, in this case any of these walls,
we get the information
about the intersection
and we flip the portal
decal so that it's
the same angle as the wall rotation.
And then what happens when we actually
collide with one of the portals just
in code if we were to think
about how to implement
the behavior that goes on here?
It's transporting the player.
And it's doing effectively setting
the player's transformed position
to the same transform
position as the portal.
Now, if we do the same
thing on the rotation,
the FPS controller's
rotation gets a bit skewed
if you mess with it's X and Z
rotation, the default controller.
So all we do for now is we just keep
those values, the X and Y rotation,
but we just change the Y rotation.
Y rotation is its position in
space like this effectively.
So that allows us to get
when we jump out of the wall,
we notice that he's flat from it, but
if we jump through any of the wall
portals-- so if you create
a portal on the wall here,
and then jump through it, you'll
notice that you're sort of angled
at the right--
and the reason that it's skewed is
because this one is upside down.
And so it's flipping the camera
that's rendering the texture
and it's looking a little bit weird.
But when you jump through, it
basically keeps your X and Z,
but rotates your Y position
so that you come out
looking as if you went straight through
the portal, rather than by default,
it has you look back at the portal that
you came out of, which is a bit weird.
Or whatever direction you
were walking through it
when you went through the portal.
AUDIENCE: How are you getting the mirror
[INAUDIBLE] so you can see yourself?
COLTON OGDEN: That's just default
because it's a render texture.
So there's a camera actually
behind each of these portals.
So the prefab is a mesh
with a render texture.
And then behind it, there's a camera.
And so, the camera is rendering in real
time what's in front of the portal,
basically, from behind it.
And so it's seeing your model
from both of these portals,
both cameras are seeing your
model, and so it shows up
in the render texture
on the other portal.
So it's effectively like looking at
two video cameras instead of a portal.
It's sort of a trick.
And this is a very crude
implementation of "Portal,"
the actual game uses a much more
sophisticated algorithm for--
and it also tracks your
position with the camera
so that based on your
angle of rotation, you'll
actually see something
different on the texture there.
But it's a lot more complicated to
put something like that together.
I have some resources that I've included
in the lecture in the assignment that
will show you actually how to do that.
But it would take many, many more hours
than I had to put this demo together.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, right
now it's just fixed.
COLTON OGDEN: Yeah it's fixed.
If you actually look
at it from the side,
you'll notice that it's
just a flat texture.
There's no perspective.
Ultimately, its perspective.
And there's an awesome
video that I'm going
to show later in the slides by a
YouTuber named Braxis where he actually
implements a perspective correct
shader that allows you to see,
and with camera tracking of the player.
Like both cameras will track
the position of the player,
as well as render a texture.
And the result of that is because the
cameras are changing their position,
it's sort of like changing the
angle at which the scene is
being rendered onto the portal mesh.
But also the way that it's being
drawn is a little bit different,
and so he has a really
cool shader that does that.
And then Vavle, when
they present, they'll
actually show how they went about
doing it, which is even more complex,
but it looks really good and is a
lot more technically interesting.
But yeah, that's my sort
bare bones implementation
of what makes "Portal" work.
And it's somewhat fun to
walk through these portals
and just sort of play around with it.
Now the reason that if you just walk
into a blue portal it doesn't work
is because the portals are actually
stored off screen until you use them.
I'll open up the scene here.
Oh, by the way, thanks
James for coming up to demo.
I appreciate it.
So the portals are over here, right?
Both of them are right here.
And so what that does is when
you only shoot one of them,
the other one is still out here,
so when you walk through it
you end up just teleporting
outside the level.
And in order to not have that
happen, what you really need to do
is have a flag on both
of them that just says
don't teleport unless you've
been shot once, right?
And that will prevent that sort
of behavior from happening.
Simple fix, but an entertaining
one to take a look at.
And that is my crude
implementation of "Portal."
It's far from being anywhere near
as polished as the actual game.
And there is the slight
weird wall that gimbal
locks the portal, which I would like
to figure out why exactly that is.
But everything else is sort of in here.
Now, it doesn't include something
like shooting blocks through it,
but the same sort of
principles would apply
because all we're effectively
doing on the portal is saying--
it's basically a trigger, right?
It's got a box collider on it, and
it says if I collide with something,
and in this case the player, I
want to teleport that collider
to the other portal, which means
that the portals sort of have
to link to each other, right?
One portal has to have a
reference to the other portal
so that it can say, "Teleport
to the linked portal."
And vise versa, the link
portal should have a reference
to the other portals
that can say, "Teleport
back if you collide with this."
And so, if we have another object-- like
say, we shoot a cube into the portal,
it would also get teleported
to the other portal, right?
And the other consideration for
that is like if its a rigid body
and it has physics applied
to it, for example,
let's say its going like 10
on the X and it teleports
to a portal that's perpendicular to
it and it's still going 10 to the X,
then as soon as it
shoots out the portal,
it's going to go straight left,
which isn't the behavior we want.
We want it to go forward.
So linear velocity
needs to be calibrated
to go in a different direction.
Didn't have enough time to put
a full demo of that together,
but if you were curious,
in a nutshell, that's
sort of like what you would
need to do in order to implement
some basic physics with "Portal."
So holding a weapon.
Based on this screen
shot, can anybody tell me
how they think I went from
just a plain FBS controller,
to an FBS controller holding a gun.
AUDIENCE: Can you
stick a gun, like one--
do they call it colored pixels--
one unit in front of the camera?
COLTON OGDEN: Yeah.
There's not really a notion
necessarily of pixels in 3D space
because that changes
depending on your resolution.
But yes, Unity units--
it's effectively equivalent
to a meter, and you can change
what it represents in Unity settings.
But yeah.
I mean, it doesn't necessarily
have to be one unit.
It can be an arbitrary amount.
And what it really was me going
into here with this model.
By the way, I got this model
on the Assess Store for free.
So the Assess Store is an
awesome place if you're looking
to just quickly prototype your game.
They didn't have any obvious portal
gun lookalikes that looked really good.
So I was like, "Oh, this guns
got like the same kind of color.
I'll just choose this.
It's like a sci-fi kind of gun."
But as you can see,
there's a hierarchy here.
Now, how are we keeping the gun
affixed to where the camera is looking,
do we know?
AUDIENCE: You do the same thing as
you do with the first person shooter
code is you have the camera
follow the gun or vice versa.
COLTON OGDEN: You have
the camera follow the gun.
Do you have any guesses
to how we're doing?
It's actually a really,
really simple thing.
AUDIENCE: I know i'm
doing it, but [INAUDIBLE]
COLTON OGDEN: So all we're doing--
Oh, Steven.
AUDIENCE: I was going to say do
you set the cameras to transform
as [INAUDIBLE].
Do the guns transform with an
offset, like in the same direction
but with a position offset?
COLTON OGDEN: Yeah.
Kind of.
Except the guns transform to the cameras
transform, but just with an offset.
And that is effectively
what we're doing.
And in order to accomplish
that, it's really
as simple as just making
it a child of that thing.
So this is the first person
character controller.
It's got a camera attached to it.
Anything that you make a
child of something else,
it's going to have the same
transform changes applied to it,
including rotation.
So by making the gun just a child
of the first person character, which
is where the camera is here--
first person character,
by the way, is just
a subcomponent of the FPS
controller, which I renamed
to portal gun FPS controller here.
The portal gun, anytime
this first person character
is rotated, which is the camera,
so anytime the camera is rotated,
it applies that rotation to the
portal gun here, this gun mesh.
And so, that gives you the effect.
So what you do is you start
it off in 3D space like this.
You're looking at your game scene,
and you have your character.
And then you move your
gun object around.
In this case, let's go
to layouts two by three.
So you can see it in real time.
This is the game view, this is what
it's going to look like on Startup.
I'm going to go over
to my editor view here.
And I'm just going to grab
the actual gun component here,
the gun object I should say.
Go and position it, and I
can just move it, right?
And so this is how you can change where
your gun is relative to the camera.
And this is going to affect
sort of how it feels, right?
Like I could put it here and it's kind
of a little lower, I could put it here,
it feels a little weird obviously
because it doesn't have a hand on it.
So it almost looks like a VR game.
And that's kind of what VR games
do is they take your hand positions
and then the gun transform is
locked to basically where your hand
controllers are.
In this case, all I did
was I just positioned it.
I said, "I like how it looks right
here, so I'm just going to do that."
And as soon as I make it a child of
the first person character, which
is the camera, it's just going to
get all the rotations applied to it.
So anytime we make any rotations to
the camera, which I'm doing here,
it stays exactly
aligned with the camera.
This applies to any operation
that you do in Unity
when you make any sort of
transform position scale changes.
They all get propagated down the chain.
All the objects that are
children of an object that
get transform operations applied to them
will have the same transform operations
applied to them.
Sort of like this
recursive kind of effect.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: So if you import
the first person controller,
[INAUDIBLE] has jump and
moves left and right.
And then you just move your asset, your
gun, to be underneath that controller,
it would just follow?
COLTON OGDEN: Correct.
So if you just import the vanilla FPS
controller, and then just make the gun.
Specifically, the gun needs to be
a child of this, the first person
character bit because
that has the camera.
And recall, the camera is what's
driving our rotation, right?
Because we're moving the
camera's rotation with our mouse.
That is ultimately
going to determine how
the transform gets applied to the gun.
But yes.
And so whenever we're doing anything in
Unity-- and you'll do a lot of things
where one things movement or scale or
rotation should apply to another thing,
just remember that's usually
just as easy as making
it a child of something else.
So any other questions as to how we've
gone about implementing the weapon?
All right.
So ray casting.
So ray casting is a nice feature
that Unity gives you for free.
It's part of the physics
sort of name space in Unity.
Part of the scripting API.
And what it allows you
to do is effectively
look at from whatever
transform you're operating at,
or whatever transform you
give it as the source,
so whatever point you give it as the
source, you can tell a direction,
give it a vector as a direction.
In this case, what we're doing is
we're saying transform.forward.
And transform.forward
just means basically
wherever we're looking X and Y, and
then straight in the Z direction.
So if you're doing it
on a camera, it's always
going to be exactly
what you're looking at.
It's always going to be
exactly forward on the--
transform.foward on a camera is always
going to be like center of the screen
wherever you're looking at.
And so if we cast a ray from
the point of our character--
or actually we're doing it
from the point of our gun,
to the transform.forward-- like a line
going from our player to transform
the forward vector of its character,
the forward vector of our camera,
it's going to have the effect of--
we can shoot something, right?
We can create a ray cast and then affix
something wherever that ray intersects.
And it'll be at the exact
center of our camera view.
Does that make sense?
So you shoot a line from your
z-axis, which is your forward vector.
And then based on how
you've rotated the camera,
X and Y are the X and Y part of
that, and Z is always forward,
that'll let you shoot things or
cast rays directly in front of you.
And you can cast rays between any
object and from any source point
with any sort of direction you want.
But it's particularly
pertinent in the context
of how we've shot it from our gun.
And so here is a screenshot
actually of what that looks like.
And so the nice thing
about Unity actually
is it has a function
called or debug.drawray,
which I'll show you here.
I implemented it in a
component called debug ray,
so that you can actually see where
a ray is being cast in your scene
and eliminate any ambiguity there.
So you can see draw ray,
transform.position, and then
we just say
transform.transfromdirection,
vector3.forward, and then times 1,000
just means 1,000 units from that point.
And then color.red.
And so what that will do
is-- only in the editor view,
so this doesn't apply
in the actual game.
This is just a debug
call, debug.drawray.
And so it'll render in this scene
up here, just not done here.
So if we hit play, I
actually have all the portals
rendering a debug ray from their
forward transform and from my gun.
So you can see it there, I'm
just doing a debug.drawray
with just transform.foward and using my
transform.position as the source point.
And notice that Z arrow.
It's always following the
same direction, right?
X and Y are sort of
changing the backplanes
sort are like how that's rotated,
but Z is always forward, right?
And so that's the ray
coming from our gun.
And if we shoot a portal there and
there, I have those also set to--
let me pause so I can rotate
the view a little bit.
I have those also set to draw a
ray from their forward position.
So those are also drawing a ray
from what's their transform.foward,
their directional vector.
But yeah, ray casting.
It's pretty easy just to get some
pretty simple collision tests this way
with guns, with a lot
of different things.
But primarily, you'll see this used
for like calculating whether something
is blocking something else.
Like if a car is moving and maybe it
detects another car, like in "Grand
Theft Auto," for example.
And your car is driving down the
center of the road or something
and it wants to know whether there's
a car two units in front of it
or something.
You just cast a ray and
see if there's any geometry
there from its forward vector, right?
Transform.position,
car.position, and then
get its forward vector, which
will be its Z direction.
And then it depends on whether
or maybe your game is top down,
maybe it's not your forward vector,
maybe it's your Y vector in that case.
But that will effectively give you--
not only that you've got a collision,
but also tell you where the
collision is too, which is nice.
And we do that in the portal gun
script where we call physics@raycast.
So this is the function, by the
way, to actually do the ray cast.
The interesting thing
about ray casting in Unity
is that it returns a struct object.
And so, you need to declare
this hit object, which
will tell you all the information
about the hit, like where
it was, whether it was
a hit to begin with,
and what the normal was on the surface
that it collided with, so the angle
at which that sort of
plane was projecting out.
And then, you call physics@raycast with
the position and a transform direction.
And then, you pass in out hit.
So out is interesting because it is
sort of C Sharp's way of allowing you
to return multiple values to something.
So out is going to be
an object, in this case,
it's going to be our ray cast hit
that we declared up here, right?
Which is a struct, which recall is just
a collection of variables like in C
or C++.
And out hit just means that normally we
pass in these values to the function,
they don't get manipulated, right?
But we pass in this
variable as out, which
will allow this function
to actually change
the data inside this hit variable.
And so the result of that
is hit from this point
forward contains all of the
information about the ray
cast that we just triggered.
And when we call
mathf.inifity, that just
means ray cast to infinity,
which is until forever and ever.
And Unity obviously
doesn't check infinitely
whether something is colliding with
something, it optimizes the right way.
But you can use that just if you
don't want to necessarily specify I
want to check two units or five units
or a thousand units front of me.
I want to just check forever
and see if it collides
with something in your scene, right?
And then as you can see here once
we have detected a collision,
we play a portal sound,
we get the right portal,
and then we set the portal's
transform and rotation
based upon the hits point and rotation.
And that's pretty much all that's
involved in shooting the gun.
And you can take a look
through here if you
want to get a sense of how it
works, and maybe explore also
the physics.raycast
section of the API just
to understand what exactly it
returns and what you can do with it.
But in this case, this
is how we're using
it to detect whether we've
intersected with the wall.
So it'll intersect
with any sort of mesh.
And then when it does, it will
tell you exactly how it did.
So that is what ray casting is.
Ray casting has another name for like
old school games like "Wolfenstein."
The method of rendering
was called ray casting
where you would generate a ray
from every pixel of the screen
effectively, although it was mostly
just every line of the screen.
And you would just look up and down for
everywhere it intersected in the scene,
and then just draw a texture there.
And so that would generate
a world that looked 3D,
but you couldn't move up and down
because it was always generating
all the rays completely forward.
And so you were locked onto two axis.
But ray casting is different in Unity.
Ray casting is just
literally casting a ray
in 3D space versus the sort
of 2D space that it was
casting in games like "Wolfenstein."
Here's another screenshot of normals
from our portals casting out rays.
And I want to look up and see if I can
find a picture of what "Wolfenstein"
looked like.
I'm pretty sure most folks are
probably familiar with not the new one.
Yeah, "Wolfenstein 3D."
So this was "Wolfenstein."
So old school, but this sort
of ray casting was different.
It would basically shoot rays from every
single line of the screen up and down.
And it would detect, based
on the level geometry-- which
was very simple level geometry.
It was just basically whether there
was a wall there or not, true or false,
kind of like a 2D image.
And it would draw,
based on how far away it
was, that particular
point of the geometry,
it would just draw pixels from a
specific texture at a specific point.
And they had to interpolate
where in the texture.
It was a little more complicated.
But in case you see ray casting
used in those two different senses--
in the case of old school
game engines, in the case
of modern Unity sort of ray casting,
that is what is involved in that.
So any questions as to how
in a nutshell the ray casting
works in the context of our game here?
AUDIENCE: Are we going to
be using the [INAUDIBLE]??
COLTON OGDEN: So unfortunately, no.
The Oculus does not work on Mac.
They do not have Mac support.
And so we were unable to
get a version of it working.
We don't have the means to necessarily
transport given how much time we had.
Now getting VR working in
Unity is actually very easy.
If I recall correctly, I have
to just remember the exact menu.
I had sort of anticipated
talking about this before.
I think it's player XR settings.
Yeah, that's it is.
So it's incredibly easy.
If you want to do a game in VR in
Unity, and you have a PC, out of the box
is very easy just to get it working.
All you need to do is go to Edit
Project Settings, and then go to Player.
And then in the XR settings-- so Unity
has deamed all of its VR AR stuff
as XR.
And you click Virtual
Reality Supported Here.
And you have your Oculus Rift
or Vibe or whatever plugged in,
it'll just work with the
camera right out of the gate.
So it's pretty easy.
You may have to install
drivers on your computer such
that your computer knows that
you have an Oculus plugged in,
but assuming that's all
set up, your project
is as easy as just
clicking this checkbox.
AUDIENCE: Which headsets
does this support?
COLTON OGDEN: HoloLens, Oculus
Rift, and I'm pretty sure the Vive.
90% sure the Vive.
I'm not 100%, we can Google it though.
Let's see.
Unity 5.
AUDIENCE: Is there a special
developer version of those headsets,
or is it [INAUDIBLE]?
COLTON OGDEN: It looks like it does.
It looks like it definitely does, yeah.
And of course, VR Windows PC is very--
I apologize.
I totally thought going into the
course that Oculus worked on a Mac.
But as of even October, they
were like it's not going
to work on any MacBook ever released.
So only on a PC, unfortunately.
That said, if you do have a
PC, super easy to get working.
And it looks like this is
actually a pretty cool tutorial.
I haven't looked at this,
but I tend to like Ray--
I don't know if his name is
Wenderlich or Wenderlich,
but he makes really good game
programming tutorials in general.
So because we're co-incidentally
here, if you guys are curious,
I really like this website
for basic tutorial stuff.
AUDIENCE: Are there other
[INAUDIBLE] coming back?
You have Vive.
COLTON OGDEN: We have Vive.
Well, the thing about Vive is you need
to install ceiling mounted cameras
in order for it to work.
So that's kind of out of the equation.
We have the Gear VR, but we would need
to export it to mobile and test it.
I didn't anticipate it
not working for Mac,
and so it kind of came up a bit late.
And so, it's on me.
I apologize.
But if you are doing a PC game in
Oculus and you want some assistance,
I'm happy to help out.
It looks like it's very easy just to get
working with the default FPS controller
camera.
So definitely reach out if
you're developing Oculus
and need some assistance.
Maybe for the our next Unity course,
we can have a big sort of VR day
where we bring in all the guns.
But, yeah.
Back to ray casting and what
we were just talking about.
Shooting a ray on your z-axis based on
your rotation, get information from it,
and then sort of what we
do is we flip the portal
based on the hit.rotation of the
surface that we collided with.
And that's effectively all
the ray casting that we
need to worry about for "Portal."
But the actual making of "Portal" is
probably the most interesting part
of this whole project.
And so let's go ahead and
go back into present mode.
So a rendered texture is the fundamental
way at which we go about doing it.
And there are various
ways to accomplish doing
it, some that are more
technically challenging
and look a lot nicer than others.
I did a sort of simple
version of it just
to get to a proof of
concept out of the gate.
But Unity makes it really easy just
to get a simple render texture up
and running.
So a rendered texture is,
recall, just a texture in Unity.
So it's an asset, it's an Unity
asset that you can create.
The difference between
a rendered texture
and a texture that you might have
imported from like Photoshop or Gimp,
is that a rendered texture
can be rendered to.
And typically, this is used for things
like cameras being rendered to it.
Although, from what I understand,
you can render anything to it.
So you can create procedural
textures this way as well.
But in this example
here, we're essentially
creating a screen into
which we're looking
at the viewpoint of our
other portal, right?
From its forward direction.
So we can see what it will look
like once we walk out of the portal
and go into the next area.
So I have some in the slides, if
you want to download the slides.
They're here.
You can see exactly how to
create a render texture,
so literally just create and then render
texture that creates a render texture.
These are the settings that I used
for the actual render texture.
So what would happen, do we think,
if we use like a low res render
texture, just logically?
Or let's say my rendered texture
was like 200 pixels by 200 pixels?
And the resolution of
our game is like 10 EDP?
AUDIENCE: Will that just be blown up?
COLTON OGDEN: It won't
be blown up because what
we're doing is we're taking a mesh,
and we're affixing the texture to it.
So it'll just scale to fill the mesh.
But what will it look
like when it's rendered?
Because it's rendering
a 200 pixel texture.
It'll apixelate it,
it'll look really nasty.
And so in order to fix that
problem, typically what you'll
do-- a smart way to do it, would be
to dynamically figure out at runtime
what's the resolution
of your game, right?
If it's going to be rendered in
various resolutions up to 4K,
maybe down to 720p.
And then create a render texture
that is the size of your game.
And then by doing that, it will ensure
that no matter what your resolution is,
it will always be 1:1 pixel ratio, even
if you're right up close to it, right?
It will fill up your whole screen.
In this case, we went
for a simpler method
so we didn't have to do any dynamic
instantiation of the rendered texture,
which you can absolutely do.
And it is the more robust way to do it.
But in this case, I
just chose 1024x1024,
figuring that that was going to be
good enough for demonstration purposes.
And most of these other settings--
I believe actually all these
other settings are completely
default render texture settings.
The only ones that changed were
this is 256x256 by default,
and it just looks really pixelated
and nasty, especially when
you're right up close to it.
And then all we need to do--
so once we've created a rendered
texture in our scene, in our assets--
so here, I'm going to go to textures.
This is where I'm showing all
my textures, whether they're
rendered textures or not.
I have these two render textures here.
And so, these are by
default, they're not
going to be mapped to anything because
they're just empty rendered textures.
We've effectively
allocated them and said
something will be rendering to these
later, but for now they're just empty,
there's placeholders, right?
They're like blank screens, but
the TV hasn't been turned on yet.
In order to actually render to
them, we go into whatever camera
we want to render it to,
render to the render texture.
Because we're effectively
taking these render textures,
and we're rendering a camera
view onto them, right?
Each of the portals has a camera
behind it looking out from it.
And so we want to take
that camera's view,
and we want to render that
onto the other portal's face.
The other portal's render
texture, the texture
that we're going to put onto it.
And so, all we need to do is
say, "Here's my orange portal.
I have my camera here.
Every camera has a target
texture just right out the gate."
So you can just say, "OK, I'm going
to take my orange portal texture,
my render texture that
has been instantiated
so it knows that it's going to be
able to receive an input source.
And I'm going to just
click and drag it there."
And it's that simple.
Now whenever you run the game, you'll
notice that your render texture
updates.
I'm not sure if it updates in
real time in the inspector,
but it renders if you're
showing it on to a--
yeah, it doesn't render
in the inspector,
but it will update if you
affix it to any other surface.
And so, what we're doing
is we're affixing it
to the meshes that are
associated with each portal.
James, did you have a question?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
How did you make the texture?
COLTON OGDEN: Oh sure,
the render texture?
So I just right click,
and then I go to create,
and then to render texture right here.
And that will give you most of the
settings that you need to get up
and running with it, and you
can assign it to a camera.
But the important thing is
do consider your resolution
for your render texture.
Make sure that it's high enough so that
your game won't look pixelated when
you're looking at it pretty close up.
AUDIENCE: So it's as easy as that?
You just make the texture
and then drag the camera?
COLTON OGDEN: Yup.
Yup.
And what that will do is
create a link between the two
so that anything the
camera sees, it's no longer
going to be rendering
to the scene or anything
like, it's just going to
render to the texture.
And actually, I think you can run
it to the scene and the texture,
but these aren't rendering
to the scene at all.
The only one rendering to the
scene is the first person character
because it's the default
camera, main camera.
AUDIENCE: What happens if you
set the resolution to [INAUDIBLE]
COLTON OGDEN: If it's
too high of a resolution,
it's just going to compress to fit
the mesh, whatever it's affixed to.
And you'll probably run
into performance problems.
But it's not going to break.
Yeah.
Because your resolution doesn't really
have an effect necessarily on whatever
is in your game world, and
that doesn't cause any issues.
It gets interpolated.
Unity will just calculate how to
render it to the screen, right?
Game textures, generally,
are very high resolution,
like 4K textures are often used, even
if you're running your game in 1080p.
And a game engine will
probably optimize it
and down sampled the texture so that
it is like actually a 1080p texture.
And you're not trying to calculate
more, draw more than you need to.
But Unity will figure that out for you.
You don't have to worry about that.
But yeah, that's what
a render texture is.
And that's how we are
creating this illusion.
Remember, everything in
the game is an illusion.
In this case, because
the textures are flat
and there's no perspective
correction, you
can see that it's a texture, even if it
is slightly convincing from far away.
Like from far away it
actually kind of looks--
I mean, I don't know if
it necessarily looks real.
I mean, it kind of does, right?
From here, it's hard to tell.
And from here it kind of looks like
we're going into another room, right?
I go like that-- well,
that's the broken wall.
When I go like that, right?
There's a portal there, and
it kind of looks like it's
a real room that we're walking through.
It's just a resolution.
But all we're doing is we're
just drawing a camera's view
onto that texture in real time.
And if you notice, when we
move, we can see the gun.
So we can see that it's
rendering it in real time.
And that's the power
of a render texture.
And this will allow you
to do all kinds of things.
You can have like TV
screens in your game
that are rendering another
part of your scene.
Obviously an example
like this where you have
a portal looking into another area.
Now if you apply a
perspective correction
to this whereby your camera actually
tracks where your player's position is
relative to the portal, you can
accomplish a much more believable look.
And you can actually make it seem as
if you're looking into another area
because the camera is literally
moving with your player.
So the cameras-- like the
stuff that it's capturing
is going to be changing in real time,
not only just your character's model,
right?
The actual angle is going to change
and therefore, be perspective correct.
And there's an awesome
tutorial that I'm going
to link to in the slides that'll
show you how to go about doing that.
And it's really awesome.
And so this is what it
ends up looking like.
This is actually before I changed--
one of the portals had a
slightly offset camera angle.
So you can see here this
is like a little bit
higher than this one is, even though
they should be exactly the same.
But it's fixed now.
So texture masking-- oh, any
questions about any of that
process before we talk
about texture masking?
OK, so texture masking
is basically the process.
So if we just take a plane and
we put a render texture onto it,
that's what it looks like.
It just looks like it's just a square.
And this could work fine if you
want sort of a square portal look,
you don't have to do any extra work.
But if you want a
circle, you can't really
create like a circle shaped plain
object, that doesn't really exist.
And even if it did, it
wouldn't be efficient,
especially if you want a very
smooth plane because everything
is triangles and polygons, right?
So if you have a
circle, it's going to be
a bunch of these fanned out
polygons, especially very high res
circle like one of these.
That's a very high res circle.
Making a polygon that looks
like that is not an optimal way
to go about solving that problem, right?
The much more optimal
way to go about solving
that problem would be to designate
certain pixels of some texture
as being pixels that we want to
read, and then certain other pixels
being not pixels that we want to read.
And therefore, produce the final image
that gets put onto a geometry, right?
And so, what we end up doing
is creating an image first.
So it's this image, which
is kind of hard to see,
but it's just a simple sort of--
can you see from there?
Yeah, you can.
So it's just a simple oval, right?
It's the exact shape that we
want our portal to look like.
And the pixels that are white are the
pixels that we're going to render,
and the pixels that are black are the
pixels that we don't want to render.
We want to consider those as
pure zero alpha effectively.
And using a awesome
shader that you can get
for free just easily on the Unity web
page-- this is just a masking shader.
And I'm not great at writing
shaders, but what this does
is turns lighting off.
First of all, what happens if we
have lighting applied to our portals?
It's going to look a
little weird, right?
You're going to get shadows
cast on your portals
and that doesn't make sense
because we're effectively
supposed to be looking into
another place, another area.
So we have shadows that are
being cast onto our thing,
we're effectively like almost seeing
like a glass door on our portal, right?
It sort of breaks the illusion.
So lighting should be off.
A lot of these things I'm
not 100% on because I'm not
great at writing shaders, but
it's a very simple, easy shader
that you can grab off
of the Unity web page.
I think I clipped the url
here at the very bottom.
But I grabbed it off
of the Unity web page.
And all it does is it adds onto your
material this second image here,
and it gets blown up a little bit
because Unity makes any texture
that you apply to
basically any texture you
put into like an image selector
will get made into a square shape.
And our image is not square shaped.
But what this does is when
you pass in this image, which
is called a coaling mask, it will
basically combine the two images
and then cancel out any of the
pixels that are black on this.
It'll effectively add the black and
white to the alpha of the texture
pixels, right?
So you can actually
make some of these gray
and then they'll have the effect of
sort of making it half transparent.
But in this case, I only went with full
transparent and full hard 255 alpha.
So we get sort of a crisp
outline for our portals.
And that's how you end up putting
together a basic sort of oval shape
on something that is just a flat mesh.
And you can do this with anything.
Anytime you need to
take away a detail that
would make making a mesh extremely
difficult or doing really cool effects,
it's often just a lot easier
to create a mask for it
and then use the right shader
that's meant to have that mask.
And then just manipulate
that however you need to.
And again, the link here
for the shader is here.
And then you can use this for
pretty much anything you want.
End result of that is we go
from having a square portal
to an elliptical portal.
So pretty nice.
I didn't have to use a
plane, but it doesn't really
make sense to use anything else because
using a cube would create depth.
We don't want the portal
to have any depth, really.
It's just should be a flat surface.
And then when we go
through it, it should just
teleport us to the other surface
to make it look sort of seamless.
I don't think there's any
other choice of geometry that
makes sense for this use case.
AUDIENCE: You wouldn't just make a
cylinder flat and have [INAUDIBLE]
project on it?
COLTON OGDEN: No, I probably wouldn't.
To make a cylinder flat and
project it and have no depth on it,
you would be able to
still see the rings on it.
And also texturing that is a
little bit more complicated
because you'd have to UV map both
your mask and your regular texture
onto that because by default
it's going to wrap it weird.
This is just a plane, so
whatever you texture map onto it
is going to be completely flat.
But a cylinder is going to
wrap it around all sides,
and it's going to look
a little bit funky.
I suppose in theory you
could use a cylinder for it,
but I think would be a
tremendous amount of work.
I don't think it would be anywhere
near as easy as getting it to work
with just a flat plane or a mesh.
Interesting idea, though.
I guess you could
theoretically create a cylinder
if you wanted to like a
bridge between two worlds
and have one end be one portal
and one end be another portal
and then be able to walk between them.
That's a cool idea, maybe
you can make that work.
But I think for this, the
plane is the right way to go.
Any more questions as to how that works?
All right.
So we'll talk about teleporting now.
So teleporting is pretty easy.
All we really need to do is
just create a mesh collider
on the portal mesh, the orange
portal and the blue portal.
And then that mesh collider
is a trigger and it
detects a collision with something else,
we can just define on trigger, enter.
And then with that, we
can teleport the collider
other to the other portals location.
So every portal, this
is the portal component,
it has a linked portal because
we need to know where to teleport
the player to the other portal.
So we need to have a
reference to its transform.
Whether it's active because
if we allow ourselves
to teleport to another portal
and another portal back and forth
without any restraints, what do
you think is going to happen?
Infinite loop.
We just get an infinite sort
of weird flickering effect.
So you need to effectively have
a toggle switch on both portals
and say as soon as I enter
a portal, I should not
be able to teleport back into it.
And as soon as I teleport
to another portal,
I should not be able to
teleport into it either.
But once you exit the portal, you
should be able to teleport back into it.
And so, what that effectively
does is we enter a portal,
it gets flagged as not teleportable.
We get teleported to the other portal.
As soon as that happens, this
portal can now be teleported into,
this portal that we're standing in
is now flagged as not teleportable.
And then we walk out of it and
we're allowed to teleport back
into that one and the other one.
So there's effectively
an on off operation
that you have to balance appropriately.
The actual "Portal" game is
a little more complicated
because they allow you to
walk in between portals.
This does not go into
that level of detail,
and it's a more complicated
problem to solve.
This example just assumes
that you walk into a portal,
you can teleport it out the other
end, and there's no in-between state.
And actually, if you're
in-between two portals,
there's a replication of geometry, which
Valve will talk about in their talk
as well, which I think
will be very interesting.
Because if you look into another portal
while you're in the middle of a portal,
you want to be able to see
yourself in that portal,
halfway in and out of that portal.
So there is a lot of
interesting considerations
for getting very
believable portal systems,
but ours is a very simple illustration.
And so, this toggle
function is all that I
have to toggle the function's
on and off capability.
And all it is just portal
active is not portal active,
and that just flips that flag.
It's super easy.
On trigger enter, we effectively cash
our position x on the x and z-axis,
so we don't rotate it
because when we rotate our x
and z on the first person
controller by default,
it causes some really weird
buggy behavior based on the way
that the FPS controller works.
So all I do is I just
cast those positions,
and then make a rotation on the y-axis.
And that'll save us that weird going
topsy turvy effect that you'll get.
If you use the FPS controller by default
and you do perform rotations on it,
you'll notice this.
So I haven't had the time to dig
in depth as to how to fix it,
but this is the way that
I was able to fix it.
For this example, at
least, only allow yourself
to rotate on the y direction, which
is where you're looking relative
to the ground plane.
And that will allow us
to rotate based on where
we're exiting the portal, at least on
the walls that are going up and down
and then have that sort
of believable effect.
It doesn't allow us to jump
down into a portal from up above
and see us coming down from
the other portal, which
is a cool effect unfortunately, but it
does allow us of to get most of the way
there.
And so, we set our position
to the other portal's position
and our rotation, but only the y.
We get the y, and then we said it
here using euler angles on our players
transform.
And then there's a
function that I created
called mouse reset, which
effectively just calls init again
on the FPS controller's rotation
on the camera and the player.
And then, that's sort of like the
hack that you need in order to--
the reason that a lot
of the weirdness exists
is because the player controller
cashes its rotation information.
And so if you perform a
rotation on your FPS controller
by hand as opposed to allowing
it to happen with the mouse,
it will immediately reset it back
to its prior position and rotation.
Which has the effect of when we
teleport from one portal to another--
even though we set our
direction of rotation
to be outside going in the direction
of where the portal is facing,
we end up having the same rotation
that we did entering the portal.
So we end up coming out of
portals often just backwards.
And so, that's just a limitation
of the first person controller,
but you can fix that by calling
mouse reset, which is a function that
essentially just calls init again.
Which init is part of the FPS
controller's mouse look object.
I won't go too much into detail
about it just because it's
a little bit arcane and the source codes
in there if you want to take a look
and dabble with it.
But effectively, preventing it from
caching its rotation information
and just hard setting it,
and then recalling the mouse
look init function, which does
the actual setting of the rotation
on the camera and the player.
A little bit weird, but
that's Unity's FPS controller,
and that's how other people
are saying to fix it.
So you could roll your own, you
can create your own FPS controller
and probably prevent
this from happening.
But if you want to use the
regular FPS controller,
that's the limitation there.
But it's mostly working
and it looks pretty good.
Some more time on it, and we could
probably make it look even better.
But for now, I think it's good.
So that's teleporting.
Set your position, and
then set your y rotation,
override the FPS controller's
default rotation caching,
and we can walk in this portal and
then instantly walk out this portal.
And that's what we see.
So any questions as to how sort
of this works in a nutshell?
Or maybe any of the
code here in our portal?
All right.
So a much better version of the portal,
at least from the rendering side,
is this video here.
So it's Braxis.
So good he explains things very well.
He's got a very high
quality to his videos.
He creates a bunch of Unity tutorials.
And in this case, he
created a portal that
used an interesting
shader that will only
render everything but geometry and also
onto a plane, in which case this plane.
And does the camera interpolation of
the player that I alluded to before,
which allows us to actually have--
so these are two separate
worlds in tandem right now.
So there's this red world
here, and then this camera
is looking at a completely
different green world that's
completely set off in the distance.
That's the exact same geometry,
but completely colored green
as opposed to red.
And if you look through here,
it's just completely seamless
and the walk through
is completely seamless.
And he goes into detail as to
how he accomplished all of this,
if you're curious.
And he provides you the shader
that you can use for free.
So definitely check that
out if that's of interest.
There's a link there in the video.
And here's a link to his YouTube series.
I put some of these in the slack because
somebody requested some AI videos.
And he has a bunch of
different AI videos
and a bunch of other really cool series.
So you can take a look
at that, if curious.
And the best version of "Portal"
obviously is the portal itself.
And Dave Kircher and Tejeev Kohli
are employees involved at Valve
who worked on "Portal," and
they'll be here on May 2
to give a talk as to all of the
technical sort of things that
went behind the scenes and
related to rendering and physics
and just getting a
believable and good feeling
experience with "Portal" for
the actual polished final game
that we're talking about.
So definitely come to that
talk if you're curious.
We're going to take a break, and
then as soon as we come back,
we're going to talk a little
bit about some new tools
that Unity has released called
ProBuilder and ProGrids.
And we'll talk about the assignment.
And that will be it for GD 50.
All right, welcome back.
This is Lecture 10.
So we talked about "Portal" before the
break, we talked about ray casting.
We talked about render
textures, what those are,
how easy it is to make those in Unity.
We talked about how to give our
first person controller a gun
so that we could actually look around
and look as if we're holding a weapon.
We talked about the portals themselves,
how we're masking out the render
texture as applied to a plane, and how
each of those has a camera behind it
so that it can render what is going
out from the portal in the direction
that it's facing.
We're going to deviate
from "Portal" now, and talk
about ProBuilder and ProGrids,
which are two tools that
are part of the new Unity 2018.1
which will allow us to actually model
geometry per the screenshot.
This is actually a level that I
created and that is in the Distro.
It will allow us to create
geometry in the actual scene view
without needing to go into a third
party program like Blender or Maya,
and have to sort of alternate
between the two and import and export
incessantly.
Not only that, but as soon
as you model something
like this in Unity in
the scene view, you
can immediately test it
for gameplay and make sure
that it actually fits what you want.
And you don't have to worry about
scale issues when you are importing
and sort of making it work, and
figuring out ultimately that, "Oh,
I don't like the way
this mesh this level is.
Let me go and tweak it and redo it."
It just allows you a ton
of ease and flexibility.
And I previously
mentioned Braxis before,
but he's got a couple
of awesome tutorials
here on ProBuilder and ProGrids
to supplement sort of what
we'll talk about today in lecture.
But if you want sort of more of a
showcase of all the features of both,
then you can look at these videos
here and get a sense of how they work.
So we're going to go ahead and just mess
around with pro builder a little bit
here in the scene view so that
we can see what it looks like.
I'm going to open up my other scene.
So I have the "Portal" scene.
If you are in the Distro,
this is where all the
stuff that we've been looking at
exists, just the "Portal" game.
There's a ProBuilder scene as well,
which I'm going to not save that.
And so this ProBuilder scene is the
level geometry that I created earlier.
Now it looks pretty horrendous because
I didn't spend a terrible amount of time
on it.
And I'm not a particularly talented
visual designer by any stretch.
Let me go ahead and make
it a little bit larger
so that we can see it a little better.
But it showcases some of
the interesting features.
So we have obviously polygonal
square shaped rectangular geometry.
We can see that some faces
are textured and some aren't.
So we can see this
face here, for example,
is just white material,
the default material.
We can see that all of these have
this brick texture, which I got off
a procedural generator
website that allows
you to choose a good
template for your texture
and then specify colors
and stuff like that.
I did the same thing for this texture.
This is another
procedural texture, which
is kind of like a blue,
marbley type texture.
The cool thing about it
is-- at least for texturing,
you can just choose arbitrary
faces that you want to texture,
rather than have to texture
the whole thing like you
would do if you were to just
give a mesh a default material,
it'll apply to the whole mesh.
In this case, it's just applying it to
whatever faces we select in ProBuilder.
Another interesting thing,
which I really like,
is ProBuilder gives you a lot of tools
for creating special kinds of geometry
very quickly and efficiently.
In this case, this is a
staircase, which all I had to do
was with ProBuilder
select build staircase,
and then you can choose a
lot of different parameters.
We'll take a look at how
to do that in a second.
I did the same thing here.
So notice this staircase
has kind of a spiral to it.
And then this staircase is
really tall, but has no spiral.
And then we have another
staircase here, which
is kind of shorter and
doesn't have a spiral,
and then it ends up coming
up here to this point.
And then if this were
the assignment, maybe
this spot here would be where
you put your collider that
says, "OH, this the level's conclusion.
You've been in the level."
So the assignment is with
ProBuilder, make a level.
It doesn't have to be
anything terribly fancy.
I'm not a great designer.
But it should have at
least one section where
you're required to jump,
so some sort of jump puzzle
just so that you can think about the
design of your level a little bit.
And it should be meaningfully large,
it doesn't have to be gargantuan.
And it shouldn't be small, it
shouldn't be 10 meters or--
maybe not 10 meters, but it
shouldn't be like five meters large.
Obviously, that's very small.
It should be something that you would
consider a somewhat sizable level.
Using something of this
size is a fair metric.
So ProBuilder-- so by
default, ProBuilder
is not installed in your project.
You have to go to the Asset Store.
I don't know, Asset Store has been a
little bit slow last couple of days.
Let's see if it works quickly.
It looks like it is.
So if we go to the Asset Store
and open-- it's connecting again,
it's being slow.
So if you search for assets and just
type ProBuilder, it will pop up here.
And notice that it says
Unity technologies.
Anything basically that
says Unity technologies
will be a free sort
of supplement to Unity
that you can easily just
import from the Asset Store.
Now it's a little bit cramped the window
here, because I'm in a 720p monitor.
But you just have to click
Download, and then Import in order
to import it into your project.
The Distro for "Portal"
for assignment 10
already has ProBuilder
and ProGrids installed.
ProGrids would be the exact same
process, just ProGrids right here.
And when you import both
of those into your project,
you'll immediately have the
ability to go up to Tools.
And you'll see ProBuilder
and ProGrids here.
And all you need to do is click on the
ProBuilder and then ProBuilder window.
And you can see here this nice
little widget filled window pops up,
and you can also dock
it here if you want to.
Actually, I did that on accident.
But Unity makes it pretty
nice so you can dock
your stuff wherever you want it to.
And there's a few different things.
So you can do new shape
and a new poly-shape.
The new shape actually
gives you shape templates.
So here, I have chosen
just cube by default,
and it allows you to do
stairs, prisms, cylinder.
So I can just do a stair,
for example, and then
we immediately see this stair mesh here.
I can generate the number of steps that
I want just by changing the slider.
I can change the curvature if I want,
so that it's a rotating staircase.
And then I can also change how
wide and how tall the stairs are,
and also this inner radius is
like how deep the steps are,
if that makes sense.
And then all of these
together, once you've finished,
you just hit build stair, and it's done.
Now you have a stair mesh that you
can just put anywhere in your level,
and it's that easy to make stairs.
Before I get into more of
what makes ProBuilder, work,
I'm going to go ahead
and enable ProGrids.
So ProGrids is a cool feature.
It's a cool add on, which will
actually lock everything in your scene
to a specific grid which you can
designate based on how fine or coarse
you want the grid to be.
And what that will allow
us to do is when I move,
notice that it's moving on the grid.
It's not moving in a continuous
motion, it's actually discrete steps.
And the advantage of
doing things this way
is that when you're modeling
your level or whatnot--
let's say you have maybe a diagram
or a drawing that you've created.
You slap it on a texture,
a flat mesh in your scene,
and then you just sort of
draw your level on top of it,
everything will map up nice and cleanly
when you're creating all your geometry.
And you can snap things together and
it will align all on the same axis.
And it makes creating levels
like this just a lot easier.
You don't have to worry about
things being slightly off
and then like missing
vertices and everything
be looking a little bit unclean.
This ensures that
everything is very clean.
So again, just notice the
discrete steps that it's moving.
These are all locked to the grid here.
And so you can change all the
settings here as to how large it is.
If I create a cube.
So I'm going to go ahead and
create a new cube and build it.
Notice up here these four buttons
are like the modes with which
we can interact with our cube.
And this is very similar to what you
get in 3D software, like Blender,
Maya, whatnot.
You choose vertices with
the left mouse, and then you
can hit shift to select multiple,
and then you can just move it.
And since I'm using ProGrids, it's
snapping it to the grid, right?
So if I turn off ProGrids, it
should just be continuous like that.
And so, you can get
whatever sort of angles
you want depending on
what your use case is.
So I'm going to go
ahead and hit Command Z.
If I click on the face mode and I
click this face and I shift click,
it'll actually extrude
it and make a new face.
And I can keep doing
this over and over again.
Let me zoom out a little bit so
I can see a little bit better.
And I extrude that, and
then I extrude that.
Right?
Starting to build something.
It's not beautiful, but it's something.
I can extrude that again.
I believe I can scale as well.
So you can build it out like that.
And I haven't spent a
ton of time mastering
how to use that tool and all the
ins and outs of it, but it is very,
I think, useful if you're
looking to get into level design
and you want to avoid the overhead
of dealing with third party
software like Blender or Maya and
having model files that you're
importing and exporting.
It can be kind of a pain.
However, if you want to export
models, you can definitely do that.
There is a method here--
I forget which one it is off hand.
I think it's this one.
No.
One of these allows
you to save the model.
I don't remember
exactly which one it is.
Is it this one?
The menu is a little bit cramped here,
so I'm going to actually blow it up.
Offhand, I can't recall which of
these allows you to actually export.
I don't have the icons memorized
yet because it's a fairly new tool.
But one of these will allow
you to actually export
the object as FBX or OBJ,
whatever your software is
that you end up wanting to--
so you can just also go up to
here to the export menu, which is
a lot easier to see everything by name.
And you can choose how
you want it to export.
You can also export
assets too for your game
so you can have objects in
your scene that ProBuilder
will generate for using, so you
can create prefabs that way.
But then here's OBJ so
that you can export it
to your 3D software of choice.
This is relevant for situations
where, for example, you
want to like rig and
model and animate a mesh.
You can't do any sort of
rigging in ProBuilder,
but you can do that
in other 3D software.
So it makes sense to export it that way.
You can also create the model here,
export it, rig it, and then re-import
it if you want to, and that's relevant.
This is a usable scene as is right now.
The lightning gets a
little bit messed up.
Notice here when you mess with
stuff, but that gets fixed.
There's of meter here where
it does some calculating.
And by default, it will actually
bake lighting on all of your objects.
But as is, this will perfectly collide
with any characters that you have.
So I have a FPS character.
I'm going to bring this
guy up, let's go ahead
and set the transform up here,
put him in the right position.
And ProGrids is attaching that, making
that grid visible next to where I am.
And you can set the axis for that.
Currently, I have it actually disabled.
So if I enable it now, this will
actually move in increments, see?
And it'll snap it to the grid perfectly.
But as I hit play, I should
just be on this mesh up here.
Yeah.
And so this is just part
of the scene now, like
as if you had made it in
Blender or Maya or whatever.
If you jump down to my actual level
and then explore it a little bit,
this is all just haphazardly created.
Stairs and other meshes and stuff.
And so, make it all the way to the top.
I fell down.
I'm also horrible at playing games.
But the beauty of it is you can
just play it instantly, right?
Right out the gate.
Now another cool thing
that I like to showcase
is we talked about gray boxing earlier.
For making interior
levels, gray boxing is
the purpose of making levels and
testing them for playability.
The cool thing about
ProBuilder is that it
has a invert normals feature,
which I think is just
generally accessible in 3D software.
I don't know offhand which menu it's in.
Actions, geometry, do I have
the right things selected?
All right, I'm going to
open up ProBuilder window.
And then one of these
is invert selection.
Sorry, wait.
Flip normals, there we go.
And so, what this does is now
this is an interior level.
So all we did before was we made a
polygonal creation of arbitrary size
and shape.
If you invert the normal--
so recall every 3D polygon,
3D surface as a normal
and whatever direction
that's facing, going the opposite
way, going towards that normal
is what gets rendered.
But behind it, if you're going in
the opposite direction of the surface
normal, it's invisible.
And so, the effect of that is if we
flip all the normals of something that
is convex, we get an interior scene.
And if we're looking
at it from the outside,
it looks a little bit weird, right?
Like we can see into it.
And this is something that you might
see like in "Minecraft," for example,
when you're looking in
part of the geometry
that you shouldn't be able to see.
You can click through the
world and see all the other
like interior parts of the
world because you've basically
gone beyond the surface
normal of that polygon,
and you're only seeing
the from that perspective
all the surface normals of polygons that
are facing in your direction in that
way.
But often, it will allow you
to look straight through all
of the other sort of cubes
that are along the way
because you're looking at all the
inverse of their surface normal,
you're looking in that direction.
And so, again, only one direction
can a polygon be lit at once.
And even if we look at it from
the top, you can see that as well.
We're looking at it from
the top, flip the normals,
it becomes a convex 3D object.
Flip them, now it's an
interior level, right?
So I'm actually going to go into this.
And I'm going to flip the normals again.
I'm going to click on this.
I have to click on a lot of these,
actually, because it split up the mesh.
But it's going to be easy enough.
I'm clicking all the
top services of this,
making sure I didn't get any
on the other side on accident.
I did not.
I'm going to extrude this, and then
I'm going to flip all the normals,
and then I'm going to take my
FPS controller, which is here,
and actually I think it's
already inside, which it is.
I'm going to hit play.
The lighting, I'm not sure
if it will be messed up.
It is messed up because it is in the
middle of calculating a bunch of stuff,
but now I've created an interior level
with the weird mesh that I had before.
And so, if you make the building
of your level this concave thing
and then you flip all the normals,
you can create an interior scene
very easily with ceiling
and everything else.
Normally otherwise, it'd be
kind of a pain in the butt.
But it makes it super easy
to do with ProBuilder.
And there's a lot of other
features, a material editor for one.
So with the material editor, you can
actually designate specific materials.
In this case, I've created
a couple of materials.
A brick texture here, and a marble
texture, which I took some textures,
created material, made the albedo
component of those materials
that texture.
And what that allows me to do is
I can select an arbitrary face.
So in this case, I'm going
to choose these faces.
And I can just click
on this brick texture.
And now, these are
textured as that brick.
It's not applying it to
the entire mesh, it's
just applying it to whatever
specific face that we want to.
And there's a UV editor, which
will allow to actually take
the mesh of your model.
In this case, this is
our entire mesh here.
Just remember, as we
talked about it last week,
everything gets cut out and made flat.
So you can sort of see--
if you remember the shape
of what we're dealing with,
all the polygons that
comprised weird, large object.
They're all now splayed out for us, so
we can just very easily take a texture
and put it wherever we want on here.
Now I don't have a ton
of experience using this,
so I'm not 100% confident in my ability
to UV map something right now in front
of you.
But the documentation on
the ProBuilder web site
goes in the detail as
to how to use this.
So if you wanted say a specific
texture to be in part of the mesh,
and then maybe another texture
to be another part of it
in a specific welded way
that's not splat onto it,
the UV editor would help you with that.
For example, a face on a
character model or something else.
Or maybe like a sign on a door
somewhere, or something like that.
You can do that all here, just
click and drag all the faces.
The faces are actually entered
dependent from one another
so that you can lay them out in a
way that fits the texture that you
are trying to map everything to.
That is ProBuilder in a nutshell.
There's a lot of features.
We don't have time to cover all of them.
And I mean, frankly, I
just don't know of all
of them super well yet just
because the technology is so new.
But I think this is going to be
a huge part of Unity's future
and making it accessible for people
that would otherwise have maybe
been turned off by the idea of modeling
their level geometry or their object
geometry.
I mean, certainly for me, now this
makes me want to make a game in Unity
right now because I know I can
instantly start creating my levels.
It's just nice and easy and convenient.
And ProGrids, you should
definitely use ProGrids in tandem
with ProBuilder so that you can
optimally rearrange things in a way
so that they're all evenly
lined up with each other.
Otherwise, you're going
to end up with issues
in manipulating their position
in a very specific way
and coming up here and
setting their values manually.
And that's just kind of
a pain, so much easier
just to snap everything to the grid,
the ProGrids, and deal with it that way.
And so, the assignment
is largely just going
to be take ProBuilder and ProGrids
and just make a level with it.
And then just take the principles that
we've learned, create a controller,
create a collider, and just
make a very simple scene.
And otherwise, probably spend your
time focused on your final project.
So any questions as to ProBuilder,
how it works, how to get it set up?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: So what would it look like--
can a character actually stand on top
of an object that had it's [INAUDIBLE]
COLTON OGDEN: No.
It should flip through it.
Let me go ahead and put this up here.
And actually I think it does
still trigger collision,
but you'll be able to see through the--
AUDIENCE: It's just visual?
COLTON OGDEN: Yeah, it's just a visual.
It's just a visual bug,
it's a lightning bug.
The physics should still apply.
I'm going to go ahead and
set the model up here.
OK.
Hit play.
No, actually it looked
like it went through it.
So it also inverts the collision box.
I've seen some games where
you can clip through something
and still collide with it.
So I think it depends on, ultimately,
the engine or the implementation
that you're using.
But in this case, when you flip the
surface normals here of this mesh,
it also flips the mesh
collider's normals.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: The obvious thing
to do would be copy it,
size it up a liitle bit,
and then not [INAUDIBLE] it.
And then you would have kind of an
inner and outer layer [INAUDIBLE]..
COLTON OGDEN: Precisely, yeah.
If you wanted, you could
make a copy of the interior.
You'd make it the same size, I suppose.
And then not flip it's normals such
that you have a shell and an interior.
Yeah, absolutely.
Yeah, it depends.
A lot of interior levels, you will never
ever be outside of their boundaries.
And so you don't often
see that happening,
but it's very much the case that
you could have that happening.
And if you have like a house
model, for example, then yeah.
You'll actually see hosue models are
modeled with walls that are two planes,
so there's a bit of thickness.
It's actually a rectangular
shape, so it allows
you to have a collision on
one side and another side
because there's two
planes of the collider,
rather than just the single plane, which
is the direction of the surface normal.
Any further questions on ProBuilder?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: So how come you can
[INAUDIBLE] through the ceiling
but not through the door.
Is there [INAUDIBLE] in the top?
COLTON OGDEN: Because the bottom's
surface normal is pointed upward.
So this right here is pointed upwards.
But notice that here, the surface
normal is actually pointed down.
So you can only collide with the
direction of the surface normal
that's facing you, if that makes sense.
You can walk towards the
direction of the surface normal,
but not against the surface
normal, if that makes sense.
That's the way that Unity calculates
its mesh renderer component.
AUDIENCE: Well, there's
also left and the right.
So the left is-- can you go
through on the left to the right?
COLTON OGDEN: You could go
through from this direction,
but you could not go
through this direction.
Because this direction, the
surface normal is pointed this way,
so if we try to walk against it,
we'll be walking against the normal.
And so, we will trigger a collision.
But if you're walking through
it in such that you're
going the same direction
as the surface normal,
so if you're coming from this direction
then it won't detect a collision.
Does that make sense?
Yeah.
What Tany suggested, which
was to make a shell around it,
would solve that problem.
So if we created this exact mesh,
duplicated it, and then inverted it,
then we would have two
of the same object,
but with normals going one
direction and normals going
the other direction such
that the mesh renderers
account for both potential
movement directions.
Cool.
All right.
Any further questions on ProBuilder?
Again, not meant to be a
comprehensive tutorial.
There's videos and documentation
that I've linked to in the slides,
but more just to illustrate
how awesome this tool is really
and that this is probably
going to save some people doing
Unity projects in time if you're doing
any asset modeling or level modeling.
Another thing that--
I didn't make a slide for it,
but which I talked about in class
was Shader Graph.
And so, a Shader Graph is
another 2018.1 feature,
which allows rather than
having to write shaders
in Shader Lab, which is Unity's
shader language, which can be quite
an experience, quite intimidating.
You can actually create them now with
this node based programming language--
not really programming
language, but this node based
programming environment, I should say.
Which will allow you to choose
all these preset nodes that
influence the shader's behavior.
And there's a lot of different kinds.
And have the result of that be you can
see your shader every step of the way,
so the shader is just a series
of transformations going
from left to right in one direction.
All of these
transformations, you can see
how they end up accumulating
to produce this final effect.
In which case here--
if it maybe kind of hard to dicern,
is a marine guy with these blue holes
that are actually masking his mesh.
And we talked about masking earlier.
This shader itself looks like it's
applying a mask with this noise that
is generating.
And it comes with noise generation
functions, generation nodes,
which will allow you to feed those
into the mass component of your shader
and then produce some very
interesting cool effects.
Otherwise, this would be kind of--
unless you're a shader expert, which I
am not, it would be pretty complicated
and non-trivial to implement
something like this with just code.
But this generates code for
you, such that you don't
have to actually write any code at all.
But you can still see
the produced shader that
gets created for you from shader graph.
I believe that it's just a
asset now, I'm not 100% sure.
I didn't test this going in.
Hopefully, I'm not just missing it.
Supposedly, you should be
able to just import it.
I'm not 100%.
Let's see how you actually-- it
said this article maybe uses it.
Via the Package Manger.
I think this is a new
Window Package Manager.
So we to Window and
then Package Manager.
And then all.
And then Shader Graph.
Yeah.
So right here.
So Window, and then Package
Manager, and then Shader Graph
and that will allow
you to import the means
by which I create these
graph layouts if you're using
2018.1, which the course is using.
But if you're at home and you're
using 2017.4, then update to 2018.1,
and you should see this
in your package manager.
And then once you do
that, you can actually
create a new Shader Graph object.
And then you'll see it as a new
window that pops up in your scene,
and then you can start adding nodes.
I don't have any
material prepared for it,
and I didn't anticipate
talking about it necessarily,
but it's something that seems
to be very game changing.
And it's something that Unreal
has had for a long time that
sort of differentiated it
from Unity, in my opinion.
And I think a very
valuable thing that they've
added that shows a lot of
awesome progress for 2018.
So, again, a link to
Braxis if you want details
on how to use-- not
only ProBuilder ProGrid,
but a lot of other awesome features of
Unity and to do a lot of cool stuff.
He makes some really cool videos.
Assignment 10, so assignment 10 is going
to be creating a level with ProBuilder
just to get your hands wet with it.
The level should be pretty complex.
So like I said earlier, not
like a finished game level.
I'm not expecting you to do
awesome, amazing, incredible things.
But a level that has maybe a few
pieces of interesting geometry,
maybe generate some stairs, has
some pipes you can generate,
and some other things.
Have a jumping puzzle in there.
So this says there should be one
jumping puzzle for the player,
the assignment doesn't
officially say it yet,
but I'm going to make
a change to make it say
that there should be a jumping puzzle.
You can interpret this however you want,
just a couple of platforms is fine.
But honestly, whatever you would like.
And have two different
textures or materials.
So you can just import
whatever texture you want,
or you can go to a website that allows
you to procedure the create a texture.
And you can assign it
to a material, put it
in the material editor of
ProBuilder, and then use
that to assign it to a face or to
the whole object, if you want to.
But there should be at
least two, not the default,
so to make it a little interesting.
You can use many more if you want
to, but only two are required.
So this should be kind
of like a complete scene.
So make a new scene separate
from the ProBuilder scene,
separate from the "Portal"
scene, include an FPS controller
so that we can move around the scene
immediately after creating the mesh,
right?
But that said, you can use
the default controller.
You don't need to do anything fancy.
And then at the very end, you
should have a trigger on a collider
somewhere, which can be invisible.
It doesn't have to be invisible,
you can make this whatever you want.
You can make like an arch or--
I don't know.
You're free to use your
imagination as much as you want,
but there needs to be some collider,
whether it's invisible or not
at the very end.
And there needs to be a trigger,
and then when you collide with it,
it should say, "Level
Complete" on the screen.
So just take a text object from
Unity 2D, part of the canvas.
If you just add a UI
text in the scene, it
will automatically add a canvas
and an event system for you.
Create the label, and then
just set it on or off,
depending on whether or not
you've collided with the trigger.
There is code for this in the helicopter
game in the "Game Over" text script.
You can see exactly how this is done.
All it effectively is setting the
color of the text to 0000 vs 0001,
or whatever color you want to
effectively just to change on the alpha
component of the text color.
And then once that's done, then
you have a complete assignment.
And then you can spend more energy.
Hopefully, this should only
take maybe an hour, maybe less.
You can spend more energy on your final
project, which will be due on the 11th.
But altogether, it's been an awesome
pleasure teaching this course.
And I hope that a lot of you were able
to learn a lot of interesting things
and hopefully were inspired to
create some of your own projects
and will continue to create some
of your own products in the future.
I certainly enjoyed making a lot of
the stuff, especially "Super Mario
Brothers."
I think that was my favorite.
But this was GD50.
So thank you so much.